<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- was: <?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?> -->
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
(Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
(using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-dprive-dtls-and-tls-profiles-07"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
  ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
  you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
  they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the
    full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="(D)TLS Authentication">Authentication and (D)TLS Profile
    for DNS-over-(D)TLS</title>

    <!-- add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <!-- Another author who claims to be an editor -->

    <author fullname="Sara Dickinson" initials="S." surname="Dickinson">
      <organization abbrev="Sinodun">Sinodun Internet
      Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Magdalen Centre</street>

          <street>Oxford Science Park</street>

          <city>Oxford</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>OX4 4GA</code>

          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sara@sinodun.com</email>

        <uri>http://sinodun.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Daniel Kahn Gillmor" initials="D." surname="Gillmor">
      <organization abbrev="ACLU">ACLU</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>125 Broad Street, 18th Floor</street>

          <city>New York</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>NY 10004</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dkg@fifthhorseman.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Cessna Business Park, Varthur Hobli</street>

          <street>Sarjapur Marathalli Outer Ring Road</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560103</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>tireddy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="October" year="2016" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill
          in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill
        in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is
        necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the
        purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to
        specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>int</area>

    <workgroup>dprive</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
        IETF is fine for individual submissions.
        If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
        which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>DNS</keyword>

    <keyword>transport</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
        files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
        output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
        keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t> This document discusses Usage Profiles, based on one or more
          authentication mechanisms, which can be used
          for DNS over Transport Layer Security (TLS) or
          Datagram TLS (DTLS).
          This document also specifies new authentication mechanisms - it describes
          several ways a DNS client can use an authentication domain name to
          authenticate a DNS server. Additionally, it defines (D)TLS profiles for DNS
          clients and servers implementing DNS-over-(D)TLS.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>DNS Privacy issues are discussed in <xref target="RFC7626"></xref>. Two documents that provide DNS
      privacy between DNS clients and DNS servers are: <list style="symbols">
          <t><xref
          target="RFC7858">Specification for DNS over Transport Layer Security (TLS)</xref>, referred to here as simply 'DNS-over-TLS'</t>

          <t><xref target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls">DNS-over-DTLS (DNSoD)</xref>, referred to here simply as 'DNS-over-DTLS'. 
          Note that this document has the Intended status of Experimental.</t>
        </list>
        Both documents are limited in scope to encrypting DNS messages between stub clients
        and recursive resolvers and the same scope is applied to this document 
        (see <xref target="Terminology"></xref> and <xref target="Scope"></xref>).
        The proposals here might be adapted or extended in future to be used for
           recursive clients and authoritative servers, but this application was out
          of scope for the Working Group charter at the time this document was finished.</t>

      <t>This document specifies two Usage Profiles (Strict and Opportunistic) 
          for <xref target="RFC6347">DTLS</xref> and <xref
            target="RFC5246">TLS</xref> which define the
          security properties a user should expect when using that profile to
          connect to the available DNS servers. <xref target="usageprofiles"></xref> presents a 
          generalised discussion of Usage Profiles by separating the Usage Profile,
          which is based purely on the
          security properties it offers the user, from the specific
          mechanism(s) that are used for authentication. The Profiles described are:
          <list style="symbols">
              <t> A Strict Profile that
               requires an encrypted connection and successful authentication of the
               DNS server which provides strong
               privacy guarantees (at the expense of providing no DNS service if this
               is not available).</t>
               <t> An Opportunistic Profile that will attempt, but does not require, encryption and 
               successful authentication; it therefore provides no privacy guarantees but 
               offers maximum chance of DNS service.</t>
          </list> </t> 

          <t>The above Usage Profiles attempt authentication of the server using at least one authentication mechanism.
              <xref target="combined-auth"></xref>  discusses how to combine authentication mechanisms
              to determine the overall authentication result.
              Depending on that overall authentication result (and whether encryption is available) the Usage Profile
              will determine if the connection should proceed, fallback or fail. </t>

             <t>One authentication mechanism is already described in <xref target="RFC7858"></xref>.
              That document specifies an SPKI based authentication mechanism for DNS-over-TLS in the context of a specific case of a Strict Usage Profile
              using that single authentication mechanism. Therefore
               the "Out-of-band Key-pinned Privacy Profile" described in 
               <xref
                 target="RFC7858"></xref> would qualify as a "Strict Usage Profile" that used
               SPKI pinning for authentication.
               </t>
               
               <t>This document extends the use of SPKI pinset based authentication so that it is considered a general
                   authentication mechanism that can be used with either DNS-over-(D)TLS Usage Profile.
                   That is, the SPKI pinset mechanism described in <xref target="RFC7858"></xref> MAY be used with
                     DNS-over-(D)TLS.</t>

           <t>This document also describes a 
               number of additional authentication mechanisms all of which
               specify how a DNS client should
              authenticate a DNS server based on an 'authentication domain name'. In particular, the 
              following is described: 
              <list style="symbols">
          <t>How a DNS client can obtain the combination of an authentication domain name and IP address for a DNS server. See <xref target="authdomainname"></xref>.</t>

          <t>What are the acceptable credentials a DNS server can present to
          prove its identity for (D)TLS authentication based on a given authentication domain
          name. See <xref target="credentials"></xref>.</t>

          <t>How a DNS client can verify that any given credential matches the
          authentication domain name obtained for a DNS server. See <xref target="credentials"></xref>.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In <xref target="tls-profile"></xref> this document defines a (D)TLS protocol profile for use with
      DNS. This profile defines the configuration options and protocol
      extensions required of both parties to optimize connection establishment
      and session resumption for transporting DNS, and to support all currently specified
      authentication mechanisms.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology" anchor="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>

      <t>Several terms are used specifically in the context of this draft:
      <list style="symbols">
          <t>DNS client: a DNS stub resolver or forwarder. In the case
          of a forwarder, the term "DNS client" is used to discuss the side
          that sends queries.</t>

          <t>DNS server: a DNS recursive resolver or forwarder. In the
          case of a forwarder, the term "DNS server" is used to discuss the
          side that responds to queries.</t>

          <t>Privacy-enabling DNS server: A DNS server that: <list
              style="symbols">
              <t>MUST implement <xref
              target="RFC7858">DNS-over-TLS</xref> and
              MAY implement <xref
              target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls">DNS-over-DTLS</xref>.</t>

              <t>Can offer at least one of the credentials described in <xref
              target="credentials"></xref>.</t>

              <t>Implements the (D)TLS profile described in <xref
              target="tls-profile"></xref>.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>(D)TLS: For brevity this term is used for statements that apply
          to both <xref target="RFC5246">Transport Layer Security</xref> and
          <xref target="RFC6347">Datagram Transport Layer Security</xref>.
          Specific terms will be used for any statement that applies to either
          protocol alone.</t>

          <t>DNS-over-(D)TLS: For brevity this term is used for statements
          that apply to both <xref
          target="RFC7858">DNS-over-TLS</xref> and <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls">DNS-over-DTLS</xref>. Specific
          terms will be used for any statement that applies to either protocol
          alone.</t>

          <t>Authentication domain name: A domain name that can be used to authenticate a 
             DNS Privacy enabling server. Sources of authentication domain names are
            discussed in  <xref target="authdomainname"></xref>.</t>

          <t>SPKI Pinsets: <xref target="RFC7858"></xref>
          describes the use of cryptographic digests to "pin" public key
          information in a manner similar to <xref
          target="RFC7469">HPKP</xref>. An SPKI pinset is a collection of
          these pins that constrains a DNS server.</t>

          <t>Authentication information: Information a DNS client may use as the basis of
              an authentication mechanism. In this context that can be either a:
              <list style="symbols">
                  <t>a SPKI pinset or</t>
                  <t>an authentication domain name</t></list> </t>

          <t>Reference Identifier: a Reference Identifier as described in
          <xref target="RFC6125"></xref>, constructed by the DNS client when
          performing TLS authentication of a DNS server.</t>

          <t>Credential: Information available for a DNS server which proves
          its identity for authentication purposes. Credentials discussed here
          include: <list style="symbols">
              <t>PKIX certificate</t>

              <t>DNSSEC validated chain to a TLSA record</t>
            </list> but may also include SPKI pinsets.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Scope" anchor="Scope">
      <t>This document is limited to describing
          <list style="symbols">
              <t>Usage Profiles based on general authentication mechanisms</t> 
              <t>The details of domain-name-based authentication of DNS
                 servers by DNS clients (as defined in the terminology section)</t>
            <t>The (D)TLS profiles needed to support authentication in DNS-over-(D)TLS.</t></list></t>

                <t>As such, the following things
      are out of scope: <list style="symbols">
          <t>Authentication of authoritative servers by recursive
          resolvers.</t>

          <t>Authentication of DNS clients by DNS servers.</t>

          <t>The details of how to perform SPKI-pinset-based authentication. This is defined in <xref
          target="RFC7858"></xref>.</t>

          <t>Any server identifier other than domain names, including IP
          address, organizational name, country of origin, etc.</t>
        </list></t>

    </section>

    <section title="Discussion">
        <t>To protect against passive attacks DNS privacy requires encrypting
        the query (and response). Such encryption typically provides integrity
        protection as a side-effect, which means on-path attackers cannot
        simply inject bogus DNS responses. For DNS privacy to also provide
        protection against active attackers pretending to be the server, the
        client must authenticate the server.</t>
        
        <t>This draft discusses Usage Profiles, which provide differing levels of 
            privacy guarantees to DNS clients, based on the requirements for 
            authentication and encryption, regardless of the context (for example,
            which network the client is connected to).
            A Usage Profile is a distinct concept to 
            a usage policy or usage model, which might dictate which Profile should be used
            in a particular context (enterprise vs coffee shop), 
            with a particular set of DNS Servers or with reference
            to other external factors. A description of the variety of usage policies
            is out of scope of this document, but may be the subject of future work.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="usageprofiles" title="Usage Profiles">
        <t>A DNS client has a choice of privacy Usage Profiles available. This
        choice is briefly discussed in both <xref
        target="RFC7858"></xref> and <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls"></xref>. These Usage
        Profiles are: <list style="symbols">
            <t>Strict Privacy: the DNS client requires both an encrypted and
            authenticated connection to a privacy-enabling DNS Server. A hard
            failure occurs if this is not available. This requires the client
            to securely obtain authentication information it can use to authenticate the
            server. This profile can include some initial meta queries
            (performed using Opportunistic Privacy) to securely obtain the IP
            address and authentication information for the privacy-enabling
            DNS server to which the DNS client will subsequently connect. The
            rationale for this is that requiring Strict Privacy for such meta
            queries would introduce significant deployment obstacles. This
            profile provides strong privacy guarantees to the client. This
            Profile is discussed in detail in <xref target="strict"></xref>.</t>

            <t>Opportunistic Privacy: the DNS client uses Opportunistic
            Security as described in <xref target="RFC7435"></xref> 
            <list style="none">
                <t>"... the use of cleartext as the baseline communication
                security policy, with encryption and authentication negotiated
                and applied to the communication when available."</t></list>
                   The use of Opportunistic Privacy is intended to support incremental deployment of
                   security capabilities with a view to widespread adoption of Strict Privacy.
                   It should be employed when the DNS client might otherwise
                   settle for cleartext; it provides the maximum protection available.
                   As described in <xref target="RFC7435"></xref> it might result in 
                   <list style="symbols">
                       <t>an encrypted and authenticated connection</t> 
                       <t>an encrypted connection</t>
                       <t>a clear text connection</t>
                       <t>hard failure</t></list>
                   depending on the fallback logic of the client, the available 
                   authentication information and the capabilities of
                   the DNS Server. In the first three cases the DNS client is willing to continue with
                   a connection to the DNS Server and perform resolution of queries.
              </t> </list></t>
              
        <t>To compare the two Usage profiles the table below shows successful Strict Privacy
            along side the 3 possible successful outcomes of Opportunistic Privacy.
            In the best case scenario for Opportunistic Privacy (an authenticated and encrypted
            connection) it is equivalent to Strict Privacy. In the worst
            case scenario it is equivalent to clear text.
            Clients using Opportunistic Privacy SHOULD try for the best case but MAY fallback to
            intermediate cases and eventually the worst case scenario in order
            to obtain a response. It therefore provides no privacy
            guarantee to the user and varying protection depending on what kind of connection is
            actually used.</t>

        <t>Note that there is no requirement in Opportunistic Security to notify
            the user what type of connection is actually used, the 'detection' described below is
            only possible if such connection information is available. However, if it 
            is available and the user
            is informed that an unencrypted connection was used to connect to a server
            then the user should assume (detect) that the connection is subject to both active and passive
            attack since the DNS queries are sent in clear text. This might be particularly useful
            if a new connection to a certain server is unencrypted when all previous
            connections were encrypted. Similarly if the user is informed that an
            encrypted but unauthenticated connection was used then user can detect that 
            the connection may be subject to active attack. This is discussed in <xref
            target="opportunistic"></xref>.</t>


        <texttable anchor="table_ex"
                   title="DNS Privacy Protection by Usage Profile and type of attacker">
          <ttcol align="center">Usage Profile</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Connection</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Passive Attacker</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="center">Active Attacker</ttcol>

          <c>Strict</c>

          <c>A, E</c>

          <c>P</c>

          <c>P</c>

          <c>Opportunistic</c>

          <c>A, E</c>

          <c>P</c>

          <c>P</c>

          <c>Opportunistic</c>

          <c>E</c>

          <c>P</c>

          <c>N, D</c>

          <c>Opportunistic</c>

          <c></c>

          <c>N, D</c>

          <c>N, D</c>

          <postamble>P == protection; N == no protection; D == detection is
          possible; A == Authenticated Connection; E == Encrypted Connection</postamble>
        </texttable>

        <t>Strict Privacy provides the strongest privacy guarantees and therefore SHOULD
        always be implemented in DNS clients along with Opportunistic Privacy.</t>

        <t>A DNS client that implements DNS-over-(D)TLS SHOULD NOT default to the use of
        clear text (no privacy).</t>

        <t>The choice between the two profiles depends on a number of factors including
        which is more important to the particular client:<list style="symbols">
        <t>DNS service at the cost of no privacy guarantee (Opportunistic) or</t>
        <t>guaranteed privacy at the potential cost of no DNS service (Strict).</t></list></t>

        <t>Additionally the two profiles require varying levels of configuration (or a
        trusted relationship with a provider) and DNS server capabilities therefore DNS
        clients will need to carefully select which profile to use based on their 
        communication privacy needs. </t>

        <t>A DNS server that implements DNS-over-TLS SHOULD provide at least one credential
        in order that those DNS clients that wish to do so are able to use Strict
        Privacy (see Section 2).</t>

        <section title="DNS Resolution">
        <t>A DNS client SHOULD select a particular Usage Profile when
        resolving a query. A DNS client MUST NOT fallback from Strict Privacy
        to Opportunistic Privacy during the resolution process as this could
        invalidate the protection offered against active attackers.</t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Authentication in DNS-over(D)TLS">
         <t>This section describes authentication mechanisms and how they can be used
         in either Strict or Opportunistic Privacy for DNS-over-(D)TLS.</t>

        <section title="DNS-over-(D)TLS Startup Configuration Problems">
          <t>Many (D)TLS clients use <xref target="RFC6125">PKIX
          authentication</xref> based on an authentication domain name for the server they are
          contacting. These clients typically first look up the server's
          network address in the DNS before making this connection. Such a DNS
          client therefore has a bootstrap problem. DNS clients typically know
          only the IP address of a DNS server.</t>

          <t>In this case, before connecting to a DNS server, a DNS client needs to
          learn the authentication domain name it should associate with the IP address of a
          DNS server for authentication purposes. Sources of authentication domains names are
          discussed in <xref target="authdomainname"></xref>.</t>

          <t>One advantage of this domain name based approach is that it
          encourages association of stable, human recognisable identifiers
          with secure DNS service providers.</t>

        </section>

        <section title="Credential Verification">
          <t>The use of SPKI pinset verification is discussed in <xref
          target="RFC7858"></xref>.</t>

          <t>In terms of domain name based verification, once an authentication domain name is
          known for a DNS server a choice of authentication mechanisms can be used for
          credential verification. <xref target="credentials"></xref> discusses these
          mechanisms in detail, namely PKIX certificate based authentication
          and DANE.</t>

          <t>Note that the use of DANE adds requirements on the ability of the
          client to get validated DNSSEC results. This is discussed in more
          detail in <xref target="dane"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="combined-auth"
                 title="Combining Authentication Mechanisms">

          <t>This draft does not make explicit recommendations about how an SPKI
          pinset based authentication mechanism should be combined with a domain
          based mechanism from an operator perspective. However it can be
          envisaged that a DNS server operator may wish to make both an SPKI
          pinset and an authentication domain name available to allow clients to choose which
          mechanism to use. Therefore, the following is guidance on how clients
          ought to behave if they choose to configure both, as is possible in
          <xref target="RFC7469">HPKP</xref>.</t>

          <t>A DNS client that is configured with both an authentication domain name and a SPKI
          pinset for a DNS server SHOULD match on both a valid credential for the
          authentication domain name and a valid SPKI pinset (if both are available)
          when connecting to that DNS server. The overall authentication result should only
          be considered successful if both authentication mechanisms are successful.</t>

          <!--<t>
                [ TODO: describe in more detail why this conservative
                approach is the right one, and what implementations should
                do if they want a more lenient approach. ]
              </t>-->
        </section>

    <section anchor="opportunistic"
             title="Authentication in Opportunistic Privacy">
      <t>An <xref target="RFC7435">Opportunistic Security</xref> profile is
      described in <xref target="RFC7858"></xref> which
      MAY be used for DNS-over-(D)TLS.</t>

      <t>DNS clients issuing queries under an opportunistic profile which know
      authentication information for a given privacy-enabling DNS server
      MAY choose to try to authenticate the server using the mechanisms
      described here. This is useful for detecting (but not preventing) active
      attack, since the fact that authentication information is available
      indicates that the server in question is a privacy-enabling DNS server
      to which it should be possible to establish an authenticated, encrypted
      connection. In this case, whilst a client cannot know the reason for an
      authentication failure, from a privacy standpoint the client should
      consider an active attack in progress and proceed under that assumption.
      Attempting authentication is also useful for debugging or diagnostic
      purposes if there are means to report the result. This information can
      provide a basis for a DNS client to switch to (preferred) Strict Privacy
      where it is viable.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="strict"
             title="Authentication in Strict Privacy">
      <t>To authenticate a privacy-enabling DNS server, a DNS client needs to
      know authentication information for each server it is willing to contact. This is
      necessary to protect against active attacks on DNS privacy.</t>

      <t>A DNS client requiring Strict Privacy MUST either use one of the
      sources listed in <xref target="identifier-sources"></xref> to obtain an
      authentication domain name for the server it contacts, or use an SPKI pinset as
      described in <xref target="RFC7858"></xref>.</t>

      <t>A DNS client requiring Strict Privacy MUST only attempt to connect to
      DNS servers for which at least on piece of authentication information is known. 
      The client MUST use the available verification mechanisms
      described in <xref target="credentials"></xref> to authenticate the
      server, and MUST abort connections to a server when no verification
      mechanism succeeds.</t>

      <t>With Strict Privacy, the DNS client MUST NOT commence sending DNS
      queries until at least one of the privacy-enabling DNS servers becomes
      available.</t>

      <t>A privacy-enabling DNS server may be temporarily unavailable when
      configuring a network. For example, for clients on networks that require
      registration through web-based login (a.k.a. "captive portals"), such
      registration may rely on DNS interception and spoofing. Techniques such
      as those used by DNSSEC-trigger <xref target="dnssec-trigger"></xref>
      MAY be used during network configuration, with the intent to transition
      to the designated privacy-enabling DNS servers after captive portal
      registration. The system MUST alert by some means that the DNS is not
      private during such bootstrap.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Implementation guidance">
      <t><xref target="tls-profile"></xref> describes the (D)TLS profile
      for DNS-over(D)TLS. Additional considerations relating to general
      implementation guidelines are discussed in both <xref
      target="security"></xref> and in <xref target="probing"></xref>.</t>
    </section>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="authdomainname" title="Sources of Authentication Domain Names">

    <section anchor="srv"
             title="In Band Sources: SRV Service Label">
      <t>This specification adds a SRV service label "domain-s" for
      privacy-enabling DNS servers.</t>

      <t>Example service records (for TLS and DTLS respectively): <list>
          <t>_domain-s._tcp.dns.example.com. SRV 0 1 853 dns1.example.com.
          _domain-s._tcp.dns.example.com. SRV 0 1 853 dns2.example.com.</t>

          <t>_domain-s._udp.dns.example.com. SRV 0 1 853 dns3.example.com.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="identifier-sources"
             title="Out of Band Sources">
      <section title="Full direct configuration">
        <t>DNS clients may be directly and securely provisioned with the
        authentication domain name of each privacy-enabling DNS server. For example, using a
        client specific configuration file or API.</t>

        <t>In this case, direct configuration for a DNS client would consist
        of both an IP address and a domain name for each DNS server.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Direct configuration of name only">

        <t>A DNS client may be configured directly and securely with only the
        authentication domain name of its privacy-enabling DNS server. For example, using a
        client specific configuration file or API.</t>

        <t>A DNS client might learn of a default recursive DNS resolver from
        an untrusted source (such as DHCP's DNS server option <xref
        target="RFC3646"></xref>). It can then use opportunistic DNS
        connections to untrusted recursive DNS resolver to establish the IP
        address of the intended privacy-enabling DNS server by doing a lookup
        of SRV records. Such records MUST be validated using DNSSEC. Private
        DNS resolution can now be done by the DNS client against the
        configured privacy-enabling DNS server.</t>

        <t>Example: <list style="symbols">
            <t>A DNSSEC validating DNS client is configured with the domain
            name dns.example.net for a privacy-enabling DNS server</t>

            <t>Using Opportunistic Privacy to a default DNS resolver
            (acquired, for example, using DHCP) the client performs look ups
            for <list style="symbols">
                <t>SRV record for _domain-s._tcp.dns.example.net to obtain the
                server host name</t>

                <t>A and/or AAAA lookups to obtain IP address for the server
                host name</t>
              </list></t>

            <t>Client validates all the records obtained in the previous step
            using DNSSEC.</t>

            <t>If the records successfully validate the client proceeds to
            connect to the privacy-enabling DNS server using Strict
            Privacy.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>A DNS client so configured that successfully connects to a
        privacy-enabling DNS server MAY choose to locally cache the looked up
        addresses in order to not have to repeat the opportunistic lookup.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="DHCP">
        <t>Some clients may have an established trust relationship with a
        known <xref target="RFC2131">DHCP</xref> server for discovering their
        network configuration. In the typical case, such a DHCP server
        provides a list of IP addresses for DNS servers (see section 3.8 of
        <xref target="RFC2132"></xref>), but does not provide a domain name
        for the DNS server itself.</t>

        <t>In the future, a DHCP server might use a DHCP extension to provide a list of
        authentication domain names for the offered DNS servers, which correspond to IP
        addresses listed.</t>

        <t>Use of such a mechanism with any DHCP server when using an Opportunistic 
            profile is reasonable, given the security expectation of that profile. 
            However when using a Strict profile the DHCP servers used as sources 
            of authentication domain names MUST be considered secure
            and trustworthy. 
           This document
        does not attempt to describe secured and trusted relationships to DHCP
        servers.</t>

        <t>It is noted (at the time of writing) that whilst some
        implementation work is in progress to secure IPv6 connections for
        DHCP, IPv4 connections have received little to no implementation
        attention in this area.</t>

      </section>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="credentials" title="Authentication Domain Name based Credential Verification">
      <section anchor="certs" title="PKIX Certificate Based Authentication">
        <t>When a DNS client configured with an authentication domain name connects to its
        configured DNS server over (D)TLS, the server may present it with an
        PKIX certificate. In order to ensure proper authentication, DNS
        clients MUST verify the entire certification path per <xref
        target="RFC5280"></xref>. The DNS client additionally uses <xref
        target="RFC6125"></xref> validation techniques to compare the domain
        name to the certificate provided.</t>

        <t>A DNS client constructs two Reference Identifiers for the server
        based on the authentication domain name: A DNS-ID and an <xref
        target="RFC4985">SRV-ID</xref>. The DNS-ID is simply the authentication domain name
        itself. The SRV-ID uses a "_domain-s." prefix. So if the configured
        authentication domain name is "dns.example.com", then the two Reference Identifiers
        are: <list style="ordered">
            <t>DNS-ID: dns.example.com</t>

            <t>SRV-ID: _domain-s.dns.example.com</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>If either of the Reference Identifiers are found in the PKIX
        certificate's subjectAltName extension as described in section 6 of
        <xref target="RFC6125"></xref>, the DNS client should accept the
        certificate for the server.</t>

        <!--<t>
              [ QUESTION: do we want to talk about multiple domain names
              for a single server here? ]
              After review, not in this version of the draft.
            </t>-->

        <t>A compliant DNS client MUST only inspect the certificate's
        subjectAltName extension for these Reference Identifiers. In
        particular, it MUST NOT inspect the Subject field itself.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="dane" title="DANE">
        <t><xref target="RFC6698">DANE</xref> provides mechanisms to root
        certificate and raw public key trust with DNSSEC. However this
        requires the DNS client to have an authentication domain name for the DNS Privacy Server
        which must be obtained via a trusted source.</t>
        
        <t>This section assumes a solid understanding of both 
            <xref target="RFC6698">DANE</xref> and 
            <xref target="RFC7671">DANE Operations</xref>. A few pertinent
            issues covered in these documents are outlined here as useful pointers,
            but familiarity with both these documents in their entirety is expected.</t>

        <t>It is noted that <xref target="RFC6698"></xref> says <list
            style="none">
            <t>"Clients that validate the DNSSEC signatures themselves MUST
            use standard DNSSEC validation procedures. Clients that rely on
            another entity to perform the DNSSEC signature validation MUST use
            a secure mechanism between themselves and the validator."</t>
          </list></t>
          
         <t>It is noted that <xref target="RFC7671"></xref> covers the following topics:
            <list style='symbols'>
                <t>Section 4.1: Opportunistic Security and PKIX Usages and Section 14:
                    Security Considerations, which both discuss the use 
                    of PKIX-TA(0) and PKIX-EE(1) for OS.</t>
                <t>Section 5: Certificate-Usage-Specific DANE Updates and Guidelines.
                    Specifically Section 5.1 which outlines the combination of
                    Certificate Usage DANE-EE(3) and Selector Usage SPKI(1) with
                    Raw Public Keys <xref target="RFC7250"></xref>.
                    Section 5.1 also discusses the security implications
                    of this mode, for example, it discusses
                    key lifetimes and specifies that validity period enforcement
                    is based solely on the TLSA RRset properties for this case. [QUESTION: Should
                    an appendix be added with an example of how to use DANE without
                    PKIX certificates?]</t>
                <t>Section 13: Operational Considerations, which discusses TLSA TTLs
                    and signature validity periods.</t>
            </list>
         </t>

        <t>The specific DANE record for a DNS Privacy Server would take the form: <list>
            <t>_853._tcp.[server-domain-name] for TLS</t>

            <t>_853._udp.[server-domain-name] for DTLS</t>
          </list></t>

        <section title="Direct DNS Lookup">
          <t>The DNS client MAY choose to perform the DNS lookups to retrieve
          the required DANE records itself. The DNS queries for such DANE
          records MAY use opportunistic encryption or be in the clear to avoid
          trust recursion. The records MUST be validated using DNSSEC as
          described above in <xref target="RFC6698"></xref>.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="TLS DNSSEC Chain extension">
          <t>The DNS client MAY offer the TLS extension described in <xref
          target="I-D.ietf-tls-dnssec-chain-extension"></xref>. If the DNS
          server supports this extension, it can provide the full chain to the
          client in the handshake.</t>

          <t>If the DNS client offers the TLS DNSSEC Chain extension, it MUST
          be capable of validating the full DNSSEC authentication chain down
          to the leaf. If the supplied DNSSEC chain does not validate, the
          client MUST ignore the DNSSEC chain and validate only via other
          supplied credentials.</t>

        </section>
      </section>
    </section>


    <section anchor="tls-profile" title="(D)TLS Protocol Profile">
      <t>This section defines the (D)TLS protocol profile of
      DNS-over-(D)TLS.</t>

      <t>There are known attacks on (D)TLS, such as machine-in-the-middle and
      protocol downgrade. These are general attacks on (D)TLS and not specific
      to DNS-over-TLS; please refer to the (D)TLS RFCs for discussion of these
      security issues.</t>

      <t>Clients and servers MUST adhere to the (D)TLS
      implementation recommendations and security considerations of <xref
      target="RFC7525"></xref> except with respect to (D)TLS version.</t> 

      <t>Since
      encryption of DNS using (D)TLS is virtually a green-field deployment DNS
      clients and server MUST implement only (D)TLS 1.2 or later.</t>

      <t>Implementations MUST NOT offer or provide TLS compression, since
      compression can leak significant amounts of information, especially to a
      network observer capable of forcing the user to do an arbitrary DNS
      lookup in the style of the <xref target="CRIME">CRIME
      attacks</xref>.</t>

      <t>Implementations compliant with this profile MUST implement all of the
      following items:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t><xref target="RFC5077">TLS session resumption without server-side
          state</xref> which eliminates the need for the server to retain
          cryptographic state for longer than necessary.</t>

          <t><xref target="RFC7250">Raw public keys</xref> which reduce the
          size of the ServerHello, and can be used by servers that cannot
          obtain certificates (e.g., DNS servers on private networks).</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Implementations compliant with this profile SHOULD implement all of
      the following items:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t><xref target="RFC7918">TLS False Start</xref>
          which reduces round-trips by allowing the TLS second flight of
          messages (ChangeCipherSpec) to also contain the (encrypted) DNS
          query</t>

          <t><xref target="RFC7924">Cached Information
          Extension</xref> which avoids transmitting the server's certificate
          and certificate chain if the client has cached that information from
          a previous TLS handshake</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>Guidance specific to TLS is provided in <xref
        target="RFC7858"></xref> and that specific to DTLS it is provided in<xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Security considerations discussed in <xref target="RFC7525"></xref>,
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls"></xref> and <xref
      target="RFC7858"></xref> apply to this
      document.</t>

      <section anchor="traffic"
               title="Counter-measures to DNS Traffic Analysis">
        <t>This section makes suggestions for measures that can reduce the
        ability of attackers to infer information pertaining to encrypted
        client queries by other means (e.g. via an analysis of encrypted
        traffic size, or via monitoring of resolver to authoritative
        traffic).</t>

        <t>DNS-over-(D)TLS clients and servers SHOULD consider implementing
        the following relevant DNS extensions <list style="symbols">
            <t><xref target="RFC7830">EDNS(0)
            padding</xref>, which allows encrypted queries and responses to
            hide their size.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>DNS-over-(D)TLS clients SHOULD consider implementing the following
        relevant DNS extensions <list style="symbols">
            <t><xref target="RFC7871">Privacy
            Election using Client Subnet in DNS Queries</xref>. If a DNS
            client does not include an EDNS0 Client Subnet Option with a
            SOURCE PREFIX-LENGTH set to 0 in a query, the DNS server may
            potentially leak client address information to the upstream
            authoritative DNS servers. A DNS client ought to be able to inform
            the DNS Resolver that it does not want any address information
            leaked, and the DNS Resolver should honor that request.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to the authors of both <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls"></xref> and <xref
      target="RFC7858"></xref> for laying the ground work
      that this draft builds on and for reviewing the contents. The authors
      would also like to thank John Dickinson, Shumon Huque, Melinda Shore,
      Gowri Visweswaran, Ray Bellis, Stephane Bortzmeyer, Jinmei Tatuya, Paul Hoffman and
      Christian Huitema for
      review and discussion of the ideas presented here.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6125"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7525"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5077"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6347"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5246"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4985"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6698"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7250"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5280"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7858"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7830"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7671"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7469"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7626"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2131"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2132"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7435"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3646"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7871"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7918"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7924"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-dprive-dnsodtls"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-tls-dnssec-chain-extension"?>

      <reference anchor="CRIME">
        <front>
          <title>The CRIME Attack</title>

          <author initials="J." surname="Rizzo"></author>

          <author initials="T." surname="Duong">
            <organization>EKOparty Security Conference</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2012" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="dnssec-trigger"
                 target="https://www.nlnetlabs.nl/projects/dnssec-trigger/">
        <front>
          <title>Dnssec-Trigger</title>

          <author>
            <organization>NLnetLabs</organization>
          </author>

          <date month="May" year="2014" />
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section anchor="probing"
             title="Server capability probing and caching by DNS clients">
      <t>This section presents a non-normative discussion of how DNS clients
      might probe for and cache privacy capabilities of DNS servers.</t>

      <t>Deployment of both DNS-over-TLS and DNS-over-DTLS will be gradual.
      Not all servers will support one or both of these protocols and the
      well-known port might be blocked by some middleboxes. Clients will be
      expected to keep track of servers that support DNS-over-TLS and/or
      DNS-over-DTLS, and those that have been previously authenticated.</t>

      <t>If no server capability information is available then (unless
      otherwise specified by the configuration of the DNS client) DNS clients
      that implement both TLS and DTLS should try to authenticate using both
      protocols before failing or falling back to a lower security. DNS
      clients using opportunistic security should try all available servers
      (possibly in parallel) in order to obtain an authenticated encrypted
      connection before falling back to a lower security. (RATIONALE: This
      approach can increase latency while discovering server capabilities but
      maximizes the chance of sending the query over an authenticated
      encrypted connection.)</t>

      <!--<t> [TODO: Should we make recommendations about what to do if
                    a previously authenticated server starts failing authentication?]
                    After review, removed for the first version.</t>-->
    </section>

    <section title="Changes between revisions">
      <t>[Note to RFC Editor: please remove this section prior to
      publication.]</t>
      
      <section title="-07 version">
           <t>Re-work of the Abstract and Introduction to better describe the contents in this version.</t>
           <t>Terminology: New definition of 'authentication information'.</t>
           <t>Scope: Changes to the Scope section.</t>
           <t>Moved discussion of combining authentication mechanism earlier.</t>
           <t>Changes to the section headings and groupings to make the presentation more logical.</t>
       </section>

      <section title="-06 version">
           <t>Introduction: Re-word discussion of Working group charter.</t>
           <t>Introduction: Re-word first and third bullet point about 'obtaining' a domain name and IP address.</t>
           <t>Introduction: Update reference to DNS-over-TLS draft.</t>
           <t>Terminology: Change forwarder/proxy to just forwarder</t>
           <t>Terminology: Add definition of 'Authentication domain name' and use this throughout</t>
           <t>Section 4.2: Remove parenthesis in the table.</t>
           <t>Section 4.2: Change the text after the table as agreed with Paul Hoffman.</t>
           <t>Section 4.3.1: Change title and remove brackets around last statement.</t>
           <t>Section 11: Split second paragraph.</t>
           <t></t>
       </section>

      <section title="-05 version">
           <t>Add more details on detecting passive attacks to section 4.2</t>
           <t>Changed X.509 to PKIX throughout</t>
           <t>Change comment about future I-D on usage policies.</t>
       </section>


      <section title="-04 version">
           <t>Introduction: Add comment that DNS-over-DTLS draft is Experiments</t>
           <t>Update 2 I-D references to RFCs.</t>
       </section>

      <section title="-03 version">
           <t>Section 9: Update DANE section with better references to RFC7671 and RFC7250</t>
       </section>

      <section title="-02 version">
          <t>Introduction: Added paragraph on the background and scope of the document.</t>
          <t>Introduction and Discussion: Added more information 
              on what a Usage profiles is (and is not) the the two presented here.</t>
          <t>Introduction: Added paragraph to make a comparison with
              the Strict profile in RFC7858 clearer.</t>
          <t>Section 4.2: Re-worked the description of Opportunistic and the table.</t>
          <t>Section 8.3: Clarified statement about use of DHCP in Opportunistic profile </t>
          <t>Title abbreviated.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="-01 version">
        <t>Section 4.2: Make clear that the Strict Privacy Profile can include
        meta queries performed using Opportunistic Privacy.</t>

        <t>Section 4.2, Table 1: Update to clarify that Opportunistic Privacy
        does not guarantee protection against passive attack.</t>

        <t>Section 4.2: Add sentence discussing client/provider trusted
        relationships.</t>

        <t>Section 5: Add more discussion of detection of active attacks when
        using Opportunistic Privacy.</t>

        <t>Section 8.2: Clarify description and example.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="draft-ietf-dprive-dtls-and-tls-profiles-00">
        <t>Re-submission of draft-dgr-dprive-dtls-and-tls-profiles with name
        change to draft-ietf-dprive-dtls-and-tls-profiles. Also minor nits
        fixed.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
